<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fourth of September. Newes from sundry places, both forraine and domestique From Venice, Rome, Spaine, France, Naples, the Palatinate, and the Low-Countries. A relation of Count Mansfeilds progresse, (his battaile with Gonsalo in his passage) till his arriuall at Breda, with the Duke of Brunswicke his valiant pursuit of Gonsalo, (being wounded) and the slaughter of 500. of his men, and the taking of certaine waggons, and Gonsales owne coath. Whereunto is added, a true and certaine report, of the lamentable shipwracke which happened at Plimoth in Deuonshire, on Munday the 19th. of August last past, with other great harme done elsewhere, by lightning and thunder on the same day.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08167</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.75</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103390</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839145</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839145</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3544</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08167)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3544)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1250:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fourth of September. Newes from sundry places, both forraine and domestique From Venice, Rome, Spaine, France, Naples, the Palatinate, and the Low-Countries. A relation of Count Mansfeilds progresse, (his battaile with Gonsalo in his passage) till his arriuall at Breda, with the Duke of Brunswicke his valiant pursuit of Gonsalo, (being wounded) and the slaughter of 500. of his men, and the taking of certaine waggons, and Gonsales owne coath. Whereunto is added, a true and certaine report, of the lamentable shipwracke which happened at Plimoth in Deuonshire, on Munday the 19th. of August last past, with other great harme done elsewhere, by lightning and thunder on the same day.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 [22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nathaniel Butter and are to be sold at his shop, at the signe of the Pyde Bull, at Saint Austins Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 5-6 repeated in number only.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 18501.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 18501 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mansfeld, Peter Ernst, --  Graf von, 1580-1626 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian, --  Herzog von Braunschweig-Wolfenbüttel, 1599-1626.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Breda (Netherlands) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3544:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3544:1"/>
            <p>The fourth of September.</p>
            <p>NEWES FROM SVNDRY PLACES, BOTH FORRAINE AND DOMESTIQVE.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Venice, Rome, Spaine, France, Naples,</hi> the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A RELATION OF COVNT MANSFEILDS PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe, (his battaile with <hi>Gonſalo</hi> in his paſſage) till his arriuall at <hi>Breda,</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> his valiant purſuit of <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalo,</hi> (being wounded) and the ſlaughter of 500. of his men, and the taking of certaine <hi>Waggons,</hi> and <hi>Gonſaloes</hi> owne <hi>Coach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is added, A TRVE AND CERTAINE REPORT, OF THE LAMENTABLE SHIPWRACKE which hapned at <hi>Plimoth</hi> in <hi>Deuonſhire,</hi> on Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt paſt, with other great harme done elſewhere, by light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and thunder on the ſame day.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Butter</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the Signe of the <hi>Pyde Bull,</hi> at <hi>Saint Auſtins</hi> Gate. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:3544:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="report">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3544:2"/>
            <head>FROM VENICE THE thirtieth of <hi>July,</hi> 1622.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey write from <hi>Millane</hi> that the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſoldiers from diuers places of that State, were commanded to meet at a certaine rendeuou's, whereupon many of them were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly charged to march towards <hi>Bormio,</hi> to oppoſe themſelues againſt the Griſons, a troupe of them being ſeene at <hi>Chiavenna</hi> intending to take a Spaniſh Poſt, but he was ſuccoured by a 150 Musketteeres, of the company of Captaine <hi>Iohn Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliona,</hi> which skirmiſhing with the Griſons aforeſaid, ſlue 14 of them and loſt but fiue of their owne.</p>
            <p>They had newes that the Griſons hauing inuaded the higher <hi>Aguedina,</hi> many of them had beſieged the Fort of <hi>Sancta Maria,</hi> and the reſt making their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions vpon the Frontiers of the Countie of <hi>Tyroll,</hi> droue great ſtore of cattell from thence, into their owne territories.</p>
            <p>And that there were daily held priuate conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, touching the departure of the Duke of <hi>Feria,</hi> (Gouernour of <hi>Millane</hi>) towards <hi>Veltolina:</hi> as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3544:3"/> that his Excellencie hauing notice that from the ſaid <hi>Veltolinat</hi> were fled and yet daily did fly about 60 ſoldiers at a time, and that (as they ſay) both for want of victuals and pay, he had giuen notice by a Proclamation that both Spaniards and Italians that here before abandoned the ſeruice of the king of Spaine, vnder whatſoeuer pretext or colour, ſhould haue their pardon, returning into the ſame within the ſpace of the next enſuing 15 daies after the Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And thoſe that came not in at the prefixed time, ſhall be baniſhed and condemned to be hanged, and euery officer as well of luſtice as Warre ſhall be authoriſed both to take and to kill them, not exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them that were fled themſelues, and afterwards reconciled.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Count di Monterei</hi> being there arriued, was royally lodged and entertained, at the charges of the ſaid Gouernor: And going to view the Caſtle, the Ordnance was at his approach brauely diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: As ſoone as he ſhall haue viſited all the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall places of this city, he intends to goe on with his iourney for Spaine.</p>
            <p>That the Griſons went from Towne to Towne, to confirme their new eſtabliſhed vnion at <hi>Coyra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that vpon the confines of the <hi>Canton</hi> of <hi>SinZ,</hi> the Catholike Suiſſers which haue beſet the paſſages to ſtop the troupes of their Enemies, had incountred one another, ſo that many of both ſides were ſlaine.</p>
            <p>By particular Letters from <hi>Veltolina,</hi> we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that the 26. of Iuly 30 companies of Griſons and Swiſſers, arriued in the territory of <hi>Chiavenna,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3544:3"/> and aſſaulting ſuddenly the Fort raiſed by the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards (about a league diſtant from the Towne afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) after they had killed ſeuen ſentinels of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Gariſon before they were aware of them, they tooke it preſently, and hauing put in the ſame 2000 men for Garriſon, they ſate downe before <hi>Chiavenna</hi> and gaue two aſſaults to the towne, but were repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſeeing that a little before their comming, 9. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of foot, and 3 troupes of horſe were receiued in the towne. And that vpon the ſame day arriued at <hi>Bormio,</hi> 130 Mule aſſes with Matches and Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder, which were ſent from <hi>Millane</hi> for the ſeruice of the king of Spaine. As likewiſe that ſixe Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>Berganio</hi> were taken priſoners in the <hi>Veltolina,</hi> intending to buy wine.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Lyons</hi> we heare, that the French King had ſent <hi>Monſieur de Clandibront</hi> towards <hi>Piemonte,</hi> to perſwade the Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> (as they ſaid) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of his deſigne and enterpriſe vpon <hi>Momferat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Genua</hi> is aduiſed, that the ſaid Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth hauing promiſed vnto the Catholike King 4. Gallies (to aſſiſt his other in the ſafe keeping of the coaſtes of Spaine) tooke order to ſend them thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Vienna</hi> they write that the Diet at <hi>Odenburgh</hi> in Hungary, went well on in the behalfe of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror. But that there was a rumor that <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> leauied new forces, none knowing there to what purpoſe. The Marqueſſe <hi>Gonzaga</hi> is not dead as we were informed lately, but in good health and well diſpoſed.</p>
            <div type="report">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3544:4"/>
               <head>From Prague.</head>
               <p>FRom <hi>Norinberg</hi> we heare, that through the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke of <hi>Bambergh,</hi> and the Marquiſat of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpach</hi> were paſſed 6000 Coſſacks, 1000 Hungarians, 1000 of the Regiment of the late deceaſed <hi>Dampiere,</hi> as many of the <hi>Walſtayniſh</hi> Regiment, 1000 Saxons, and 1000 of the <hi>Holſtayniſh</hi> Regiment, being all on horſe, and ſent to the Palatinate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From Rome the 23. of July.</head>
               <p>LAſt Sunday went the Pope to the Church of Saint <hi>Paulino,</hi> neere vnto the barefooted and reformed <hi>Carmeliton</hi> Fathers, and ſaid there a ſtill or ſilent Maſſe, in the preſence of twenty Cardinals, beſides two Ambaſſadors, one of the Emperors, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the States of <hi>Venice,</hi> and afterwards they ſung <hi>Te Deum Laudamus,</hi> to giue his ſacred maieſtie thanks for the victory obtained by the Bauarian Campe, and their Catholike league againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſtadt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Signior Rinaldo Arioſti</hi> who attended the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Goradino</hi> in his Chamber, is made by the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Lodoviſio,</hi> great Maſter of his horſe, in the place of <hi>Signior Philippo Malucci,</hi> who was returned into his owne Countrey.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3544:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Signiar Anaſtaſio Chianderoti</hi> of <hi>Terni</hi> is made a Collonell at <hi>Ferara,</hi> where hee was Generall before, which place was now taken from him.</p>
               <p>The Prince of Saint <hi>Gregory,</hi> extraordinary Ambaſſador of the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> had wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday laſt audience by the Pope, and tooke his leaue to returne to his owne Principality and Lands, and from thence to the Duke dome of <hi>Parma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Monte Marana</hi> in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Naples</hi> who was come here to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and queſtioned, is lately deceaſed.</p>
               <p>Thurſday laſt about the euening arriued here the Auditor of <hi>Monſieur Donabeto,</hi> Vice legat of that State, but we can not learne the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which moued him to the ſame: And it is related that at his departure the Marqueſſe of <hi>Maletefia</hi> (Generall of the Campe) was very ſicke.</p>
               <p>There was of late a diſſention riſen betwixt the Vice-roy of <hi>Naples,</hi> and the Prior <hi>Aldobran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dino,</hi> Generall of the Gallies of the Pope, which hapned by a fray or tumult, betwixt the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh watch, and ſome of his, who ſeeing that one of the Galleys was taken priſoner; they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcued
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3544:5"/> him againe. Whereupon the Counſell of ſtate being called, it was preſently ordered, that as many as could be gotten of them ſhould be clapt vp.</p>
               <p>And hapning afterwards that a Captaine and thirty ſix ſoldiers, were taken and put in the priſon within the Caſtle, three Sicilians had the <hi>Stroppa de Corda,</hi> and were condemned for ten yeeres vpon the Galleys, but were preſently within the ſpace of few daies diſmis'd with the reſt by a warrant of the Vice-roy, and went to their Galleys, ſayling ſoone after their relaxation to <hi>Meſsina.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But there was a Poſt diſpatch'd from hence, with a commiſſion to cauſe them to returne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to <hi>Civita Vecchia:</hi> Seeing they were infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med here, that this yeere the Turkiſh Galleys of <hi>Biſerta</hi> were not able to ſet forth, all their ſlaues and great ſtore of their ſoldiers being dead, whole <hi>Barbarie</hi> being likewiſe mightily inuaded with the plague: And ſeeing the Turks were not to bring any Nauy this yeere at Sea, it ſhould not bee neceſſary to ſend any from <hi>Sicilia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is arriued the <hi>Perſian</hi> Ambaſſador com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming lately from Spaine.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3544:5"/>
            <head>The Copy of a Letter from Bruſſels, dated the 23 of <hi>Aug.</hi> concerning the Progreſſe and Reſolution of <hi>Count Mansfield,</hi> ſince his being in Lorraine. With his laſt Conflict and Victory with <hi>Gonſalo,</hi> the 19. of <hi>Aug.</hi> in Brabant.</head>
            <p>SIr, I know you cannot be ignorant of the various reports ſpred abroad (throughout all theſe parts of Chriſtendome) of <hi>Count Mansfields</hi> being for theſe two monthes paſt: Some affirming that hee is very weake; others, that he is very ſtrong: ſome, that hee ſhould be entertained by the French King, and that he ſhould be falne off from the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> vpon a breach betwixt them; and that there ſhould be a mutiny in their Army, whereupon they ſhould bee vtterly diſperſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Count Mansfield</hi> being paſſed through <hi>Loraine,</hi> (where he payed for what he tooke, and commanded his Souldiers to forbeare doing any wrong, or taking any thing from any of the Duke of <hi>Loraines</hi> Subiects; notwithſtanding, at a place or two his Souldiers of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſome violence.) ariuing in <hi>Champaigne,</hi> made his Randeuow vpon the Frontier thereof, almoſt for this two monthes. In the meane time the French King made great preparation, as fearing leſt he ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3544:6"/> his Countrey: but vpon triall he found him to come not as an enemy, but as one who intended to doe him ſeruice, and did thereupon giue command to Duke <hi>Deniuers</hi> to treate with the ſaid C. <hi>Mansfield</hi> vpon certaine Articles or propoſitions, namely, on the Kings behalfe: <hi>Deniuers</hi> propounded vnto him both honors and profits, as that he would make him a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall of France, and a Generall of certain forces which he would ſend for the recouery of the <hi>Valtoline;</hi> that he would giue him 200000. Crownes in hand, and 20000. Crownes <hi>per annum. Mansfield</hi> on the other ſide was to bring to the Kings ſeruice of his Army 6000. foot, and 2000. Horſe, which ſhould preſently receiue pay of his Maieſty. But <hi>Mansfield</hi> hauing a farther reach (as by the ſequell appeares) intends no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe by the ſaid treaty, but to get himſelfe more aduantage, and to preuent ſuſpition in the matters which he directly intended, namely, for the ioyning with the <hi>Hollanders:</hi> For being at a towne called <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoon,</hi> on the Frontiers of France, hee gaue out of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> and he were fallen out, and that he was fallen from the ſaid Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke:</hi> and had ſecured himſelfe in the ſtrong Towne of <hi>Moſoon,</hi> and would ioyne with the French King; by which policy, the way to <hi>Brabant</hi> was the more ſecure, and his enemy <hi>Gonſalo</hi> made the leſſe haſte after him: For this treaty of his with the French King, did ſo amaze his enemies that they knew no other but that hee would haue concluded with him, on the contrary you ſhall vnderſtand, about the 16 day of this month, in the night (hauing before ſelected out 6000. of his beſt horſe, whereof 2. thouſand are Carabins or light
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3544:6"/> horſe, and 3000. ſpeciall footmen: which ſaid foote he likewiſe prouided horſe for the moſt part of them) marched away from <hi>Moſoon</hi> vnexpected, towards <hi>Mouns</hi> in <hi>Henalt,</hi> where he ariued the 18 of this month near the Riuer of the <hi>Mozel</hi> with the D. of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> leauing behind 8000. foot, and 1000. horſe, with all his Canon, and the moſt part of their baggage to the command of the Duke of <hi>Bulloin,</hi> and thoſe of the religion. On the way before they came to <hi>Mouns,</hi> they burnt and pillaged diuers villages, and ſacked two rich Monaſteries in the Archdutches dominions.</p>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From Bruſſels.</head>
               <p>IT is likewiſe aduertiſed by other Letters on Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day laſt, that they were come to a Caſtle called <hi>Montemaria</hi> on the borders of <hi>Brabant,</hi> and that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming through <hi>Henalt</hi> the people of the Country made all the powers they could on the ſuddaine to reſiſt them; thoſe which reſiſted him were by the <hi>Manſfiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> put to the ſword, a great number of them, and the reſt forced to flie for their liues.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Cordua</hi> with 8000. foot and 2000. horſe, moſt being <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Italians</hi> doe follow them, but are not within two daies iourney of them: Beſides, they cannot march halfe ſo farre in a day as <hi>Mansfield</hi> doth with his horſe, being quit of his Canon and Baggage. <hi>Gonſalo</hi> had thought to haue way-laid his paſſage through <hi>Henalt,</hi> by ioyning his ten thouſand old Souldiers which thoſe of the Country, had not <hi>Mansfield</hi> dealt the more politiquely in the buſineſſe; as by this following Letter may appeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3544:7"/>
               <head>The Letter.</head>
               <p>DEare and much reſpected friend, all the Newes that I haue to ſend you, is this, That <hi>Count Mansfield</hi> is come downe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Brabant,</hi> and burneth and ſpoyleth the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, marching his Army which conſiſteth of 6000. horſe, and 3000. Muſquiters on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe, for the ſpeedy diſpatching of his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>The manner of his fight is thus; The tenth man of the Muſquiteers, holding the horſe of the reſt, the reſt ſet themſelues in battaile: the 6000 horſemen firſt giues the aſſault, and the footmen powder vpon them with their Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiteers, whilſt the horſemen wheele about and come in againe: and then if there be need, the Muſquiteers returne againe for their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour: if otherwiſe the buſines bee diſpatched, they all on horſe backe get them gone with the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3544:7"/> prey that they deuoure and ſpoyle, no army of foot being able to doe any thing againſt them: and <hi>Spinola</hi> with all his horſe being not able to make ſuch an army.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> comes ſlowly forward with a great army; <hi>Mansfield</hi> hauing made way in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing the Obſtacles for his ſafe paſſage: they are within 6. Leagues of <hi>Bruſſels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee that reported this, ſayth he ſaw <hi>Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> with his own eyes, being a Gentleman that came from the Palatinat.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="report">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3544:8"/>
            <head>A LAMENTABLE RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of a great and fearefull ſtorme and Tempeſt, of Winde, Thunder and Lightning, Which happened in <hi>Deuon</hi> and <hi>Somerſet</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire on Sunday and Munday the 18. and 19. day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt.</head>
            <p>TO collect out of Stories the many and wonderfull iudgements of God from time to time ſhewed and executed vpon the ſonnes of men, is a labour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my purpoſe at this time to vndertake, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will onely relate vnto you a ſtory of a late won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull and lamentable accident, which happened in <hi>Deuonſhire,</hi> and there in chiefly of a ſhipwracke in <hi>Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water</hi> rode by <hi>Plimouth,</hi> on Sunday night and Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day morning the 18. and 19. of Auguſt laſt. There be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing floting in the Rode of <hi>Catwater</hi> diuers ſhips, ſome newly ariued, others bound out for ſeuerall places; among the reſt, two Merchants ſhips hired by Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeur <hi>Sabeſa</hi> to tranſport certaine men for Rochell, both which ſhips being preparing, and partly proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of their men, the one was caſt away with other ſhips and barkes riding in the ſaid Rode aforeſaid: The other onely buldge. But before this ſtorme aroſe, I will not omit to ſet downe a ſtrange accident which happened in one of the ſhips, there being in her both Mariners and Souldiers. About ſome three dayes before the ſtorme, one man in her ſeeming to be fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3544:8"/> or ſicke of ſome violent diſeaſe, required leaue to goe a ſhore, for his time was come and hee muſt away. The Captaine notwithſtanding would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him; inſomuch that the fellow ſaid, If they would not let him goe it would bee the worſe for them all; for, ſaid he, doe you not ſee two deuils yonder, and pointed with his finger; nay, ſaid he, there will come three more anon. They notwithſtanding cauſed him to be bound and put in the ſtrongeſt hold of the ſhip, vnder hatches, the hatches being cloſe kept downe: but about the euening when they were at prayers, hee came vp and walked on the hatches a while, whereat they were much amazed, till on a ſuddaine he leaped ouer board, and after him ſeemed to leape a thing like a great maſtiffe dog; whereupon did ariſe ſuch a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous ſtorme of wind, thunder, and lightning, that the ſhip wherein this miſerable wretch was, left her anckers, and was ſplit on the Rockes, and all her men except about 8. were caſt away; ſome of them being caſt vp vpon the rockes, and a proper Gentleman a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, was for certaine dayes ſtanding vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right betwixt two rockes, as though he were aliue, and impoſſible to be got out vnleſſe the rockes bee beaten away. In the ſaid rode were likewiſe caſt away ſeuen other Ships &amp; Barks, one wherof was driuen with the violence of the ſtorme, vpon the top of a hie rock, not much impaired, ſo ſtrangely that it is thought a thing impoſſible it ſhould come there, and is as impoſſible to be gotten off againe without ſpoyling, beeing dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo farre from the water: In this ſtorme is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bee loſt out of theſe 8. ſhips 300. men, beſides the Ships and goods. At the ſame time in diuers other
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3544:9"/> places beſides, were many ſhips caſt away, ſo that it is thought the loſſe by ſhipwracke in the weſt parts of England is 40. or 50000. pounds.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the hurt done by land, by thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and lightning the ſame time through <hi>Deuonſhire</hi> and <hi>Summerſetſhire;</hi> in many places whole fields of Corne blaſted, ſtackes of Corne blaſted and ſcorched, nay the violence of the winde and thunder was ſuch, that is ſcatttered and diſperſed the Corne as if it had beene ſowne againe, and as if God would not ſuffer vs to reape the fruits of the earth, but would ſcatter it againe, nay out of the eares, as if the flayle had beene vpon it. Let vs compare the mildew and blaſting ſent vpon our fields in generall, in the prime of our hope, before our harueſt, and now in harueſt (vpon that litle remainder) with this ſudden judgement of winde and lightning, and conſider whether we haue not cauſe to repent and to feare leſt God may puniſh vs in greater meaſure hereafter.</p>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From the Hage the 18. of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>That his Excellency the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> hath prepared Stables and all other proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for 8000. horſe at <hi>Breda,</hi> againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> and <hi>Mansfield,</hi> and hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed his brother <hi>Count Henry</hi> 6000. choſen foote, and 1500. ſpeciall horſe, to make al ſpeed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3544:9"/> by marching Night and Day till he meete and bee ioyned with the Duke of <hi>Brvnſwicke</hi> and Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> the better to encounter with <hi>Spinola</hi> or <hi>Gonzales</hi> forces.</p>
               <p>It is certaine that <hi>Mansfield, Brunſwicke,</hi> and <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zalo</hi> haue met, but none as yet can truly report any particulars, whether hath had the greater loſſe, but howſoeuer <hi>Mansfield</hi> is Ioyned with the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> at <hi>Breda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>Heidelbergh, Mainbeim,</hi> and <hi>Franckendale,</hi> in regard of the Country being waſted, &amp; through feare of want of Victuals within the Townes and doubting leaſt the Enemy Monſieur <hi>Tilly</hi> (who lyes neare them with 20000. men beſides 4000. Coſſackes, Polackes, and Hungarian Horſemen) ſhould beſiege them againe, are forced to turne out of their Townes all ſuperfluous people aſwell In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants as others, and to leaue them to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull hand of their gracious God, without whoſe miraculous preſeruation they are like to periſh for want of ſuſtenance, this is all the comfort that we at this preſent can affoord them, nor any other aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance haue wee that our ſelues in ſhort time ſhall not follow them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leopoldus</hi> the 12. of this Month, with an Army 12000. beſieged <hi>Germiſhem</hi> or <hi>Germſtadt,</hi> wherein were 500. Dutch and 200. Switzers, being the laſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3544:10"/> Towne (except the 3. former) which hath ſtood out vntaken, and hauing taken the ſame put them all to the Sword.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Saxon</hi> hearing of ſome ſtirre ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in <hi>Siteſia</hi> and ſome part of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Emperour, is gone vp with Forces to preuent all danger that may happen in thoſe partes, before the returne of his Maieſty from <hi>Vienna,</hi> hee hath likewiſe cauſed 4. pieces of Cannon to be ſent from <hi>Prague</hi> for the beſieging of <hi>Glats,</hi> which yet holdes out for the King of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From Vienna.</head>
               <p>That the Emperour is vpon his returne from <hi>Hungary,</hi> where hee hath receiued reaſonable good content. In the meane time <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> and the Lord <hi>Budiany</hi> are leauying of great Forces, and as ſome think it is by reaſon of the ſtirre of the Turks in nether <hi>Hungary,</hi> others thinke their forces are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring to ioyne and to aſſiſt the Marquis <hi>Iagerſdorp</hi> and the Count of <hi>Thorne,</hi> and to giue the Emperour his welcome home at his returne to <hi>Sileſia</hi> and <hi>Morauia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From Rome.</head>
               <p>That Sir <hi>Robert Sherley</hi> hath beene ſent from the Emperour of <hi>Perſia</hi> to diuers Princes, and that hee is arriued heere from <hi>Spaine,</hi> and from hence hee is to go to the Princes of <hi>Jtaly,</hi> and ſo to the Emperor,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3544:10"/> for ſoliciting them to a common League and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination againſt the New Turke, to ioyne their powers together for the Inuading his Dominions, now at this time hauing ſo faire an occaſion, there being a great Diuiſion now amongſt them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From Venice.</head>
               <p>That there are certaine Viceer Baſhawes reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and come away as farre as <hi>Adrianople,</hi> with a great number of Ships and Gallyes towards the Blacke Sea, where they are to ioyne with certaine Coſſackes and other to make a head of Rebellion againſt the now preſent Emperour of the Turkes.</p>
               <p>It is likewiſe written, that the great Aga Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the <hi>Saraglio,</hi> hath plotted to take away the liues of <hi>Oſmands</hi> two Brethren, the one being a Youth of a 11. yeares olde, the other of 12. but the Mother of them hauing intelligence of it, cauſed them to be conueyed away, by which meanes ſhe preuented the Conſpiracy, and cauſed the ſaid Aga with diuers Confederates, to be taken &amp; Executed.</p>
               <p>There ceaſeth not daily to be fallings out amongſt the <hi>Janizaries</hi> and other, which the <hi>Muſti</hi> ſeeketh by all meanes to appeaſe. The new Emperour the better to eſtabliſh himſelfe, hath made choyſe of the Baſhaw of <hi>Cayro</hi> to bee his chiefe Viceer Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw, vnto whom he hath giuen his Siſter in Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3544:11"/> being a very diſcreet experienced man, and on who is like to ſettle Peace and quiet in the Citty of of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> if not in all Turky beſides.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From Genoway the 15. of Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath taken vp the 15. of this Month, 300000. Crownes more, and cauſed it to be ſent to <hi>Antwerpe</hi> for the payment of <hi>Spinola</hi> his Souldiers. Thoſe of <hi>Genoway</hi> haue likewiſe granted to lend the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> 4. Gallyes furniſhed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Commaund of Prince <hi>Doria,</hi> with other Gallyes from the Pope and the Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> with thoſe of <hi>Malta</hi> for the aſſiſting of him againſt the Pirates of <hi>Argier,</hi> who are ſaid to bee Ioyned with the <hi>Hollander,</hi> and haue made a great Nauy, wherewith they haue inuaded ſome part of the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> Territories, ouer againſt the Coaſt of <hi>Barbary,</hi> rather then the Iland of <hi>Mamora,</hi> as was formerly ſuſpected.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From France.</head>
               <p>His Maieſty hauing (himſelfe in perſon) taken the Towne of <hi>Louening</hi> in <hi>Lanquedocke,</hi> betwixt <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres</hi> and <hi>Mountaubon,</hi> The chiefe Citizens comming foorth of the Towne and meeting the King with the Keyes of the Gates in their hands, being vpon tearmes of Compoſition, did for their reſiſtance cauſe them to bee Hanged, and likewiſe cauſed a great number of the Towne to bee put to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3544:11"/> Sword, vpon the yeelding vp of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe it is ſaid, that hee hath taken in the Towne of <hi>Semers,</hi> a Towne of great conſequence to thoſe of the Religion, ſince he hath made Duke <hi>Dediguires</hi> Generall of his Army, and Gouernor of <hi>Dolphin,</hi> who before was but Lieutenant, and in his place is his Sonne in Law Monſieur <hi>Criki</hi> made Lieutenant of <hi>Dolphini,</hi> who is now gone to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege <hi>Mompelier</hi> with 20. pieces of Cannon.</p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Dediguiers</hi> treating with Duke <hi>de Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,</hi> offered him very Honourable conditions, if hee will lay downe his Armes and come vnto his Maieſty, who as yet bides conſtant and his Army encreaſeth daily, and that he prepares for the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Siege.</p>
               <p>It is certainely written from <hi>France,</hi> that Monſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur <hi>Chatilion</hi> is reuolted to the Kings ſide, being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Commander of a Towne called <hi>Egremorts</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Proteſtants, which hee hath deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp, and whereupou he is made one of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals of <hi>France,</hi> and is at this preſent in the Kings Army with <hi>Dedigueirs,</hi> at the ſiege of <hi>Mompelier,</hi> or rather of <hi>Caſtres,</hi> being hard by <hi>Mompelier,</hi> &amp; more eaſie to be taken.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="report">
               <head>From Rochell the 8. of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>A French Marchant arriuing heere in <hi>London</hi> on Saturday laſt, reporteth as followeth: That when
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3544:12"/> hee came from thence it was the 18. of this inſtant Month, hee left in the Citty of <hi>Rochell</hi> 5000. braue Souldiers of ſeuerall Nations, beſides the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants and thoſe Souldiers of the Citty, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Scots, Dutch</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> ouer whom Monſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur <hi>de Fauours</hi> is Commander, a man of great Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and Valour, in the former Kings warres, who doth daily ſalley out of the Town both with horſe and foote, defeating the aduerſe part, and bringing in Cattle and other prouiſion daily.</p>
               <p>The Count of <hi>Soyſons</hi> being Commander of the Kings Army, hath built a Fort and mounted a piece of Cannon thereupon, whereby he hath annoyed ſome of the higheſt built houſes in the Towne, but through often ſhooting off, 4. or 5. of the ſaid Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons are become vnſeruiceable, being broken.</p>
               <p>The Towne on the other ſide haue done the Kings Army greater hurt, and haue themſelues ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and made vnſeruiceable diuers of the Kings Cannon, and haue poyſoned all the Fountaines round about the Citty neere the Army, whereby the Souldiers of Count <hi>de Soyſons</hi> dye daily, but they haue (in regard of the reſpect and Honor they beare him) aduertiſed the ſaid Count thereof, that be may the better auoyde the ſame.</p>
               <p>The ſame Marchant reports what hee likewiſe ſaw? comming from <hi>Rochell</hi> in the ſaid Riuer were
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3544:12"/> 16. Ships (accuſtomed to goe to New found Land) prepared and furniſhed ready for Warliike ſeruice, and were appointed to goe and encounter with the King his Gallyes whereſoeuer they ſhall meete, and ſayling further ſome 10. Leagues from <hi>Rochell</hi> neere the Ile <hi>de Deu,</hi> came by the Kings Fleete con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of 46. Sayle of Ships, beſides 13. expected from St. <hi>Malloes,</hi> with 10. Gallyes of <hi>Burwayes,</hi> all which Ships makes 59. Sayle, the 10. Gallyes being appointed to meete with the 16. Fiſher Ships, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, The <hi>Rochell</hi> Fleete at the ſame time being but 40. Ships ioyned, but expected 20. more houre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Ile of <hi>Rees</hi> to come to them, and being within 8. Leagues of the Kings Fleete, ſince which time there is newes come to my Lord the French Ambaſſadour, that within 4. dayes after this Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant paſſed by them, the two Fleetes met and had a cruell Fight, but the particulars where of and who had the better are not yet knowne, for within 3. dayes after, the Secretary of State at <hi>Paris</hi> had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the ſame, but could not vnderſtand the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, nor who had the better of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3544:13"/>
               <head>The Coppy of a Letter from Breda.</head>
               <p>Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> hauing intelligence of <hi>Don Cordua's</hi> Approach, ſent certaine Troopes to poſſeſſe ſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to hinder his March, but theſe looſing the direct way were defeated and put to flight by the Forces of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Liege,</hi> whereupon Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> reſolued to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to march with his whole Army to the aforeſaid paſſage, being there arriued, the Enemy appeared in ſight, preſently Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> burned his Baggage and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the Battaile, which continued long and furious, in the end <hi>Don Coraua</hi> was forced to retire, &amp; in the retreat the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> was ſhot and hurt, whereat being inraged the more in regard hee was wounded in the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies retreat, he diſarmed himſelfe and ſhifted his Beuer, thus onely with his Hat and Caſſocke hee made choiſe of ſome Regiments, and with them reſolutely aſſayled the retiring Enemy, ſlew 500. of their men, and ſeazed vpon ſundry Waggons richly laden, and alſo tooke <hi>Don Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua's</hi> owne Coach, wherein the Duke made to the <hi>Hage</hi> in Triumph.</p>
               <p>It is alſo certified from a Commaunder in <hi>Borgen,</hi> that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> hauing ſurpriſed two pieces of Cannon of the Enemies, he afterwards tooke a Coach of <hi>Don Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua's</hi> wherein was a good quantity of pieces of Siluer of value 5. ſhillings Sterling, wherewith Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> in a Brauado charged their owne Ordinance, and ſlew many of them with their owne Coyne.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3544:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
